<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3b2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
	
	<bookinfo>
		
		<title>Lack of Progress Bar (Lopb) - User Guide</title>
		
		<authorgroup> <author>
			<firstname>Alex</firstname>
			<surname>De Marco</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address><email>alex@lopb.org</email></address>
			</affiliation> </author> <author>
			<firstname>Aaron</firstname>
			<surname>Silinskas</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address><email>aaron@lopb.org</email></address>
			</affiliation> </author> <author>
			<firstname>Abhishek</firstname>
			<surname>Nath</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address><email>abhishek@lopb.org</email></address>
			</affiliation> </author>
		</authorgroup>
		
		<date>2009-05-24</date>
		<releaseinfo>@VERSION@</releaseinfo>
		
		<copyright>
			<year>2009</year>
			<holder>Alex De Marco, Aaron Silinskas, Abhishek Nath</holder>
		</copyright>
		<legalnotice>
			
			<para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
				under the terms of the <ulink
					url="http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html">Eclipse
				Public License, Version 1.0</ulink>.</para>
			
		</legalnotice>
		
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>Lack of Progress Bar</keyword>
			<keyword>eclipse</keyword>
			<keyword>documentation</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		
	</bookinfo>
	
	<chapter id="gettingStarted">
		
		<title>Getting started</title>
		
		<para>Lack of Progress Bar (Lopb) is a performance benchmarking tool for your
			software development environment. Lopb can be used to monitor and optimize the
			performance of tools and infrastructure that developers access through their
			Eclipse-based IDE.</para>
		
		<para>To install Lopb in your Eclipse environment, see Installation. To read about
			how Lopb works, see the section on Concepts. For a description of Lopb Features,
			see the Lopb Features section. For examples of the types of reports that can be
			produced with the data provided by Lopb, see the Reporting Cookbook section.
			Finally, for answers to frequently asked questions, please refer to the
			FAQ.</para>
		
		<para>If you have any questions about Lopb or are interested in contributing to the
			project, please send us an email at support@lopb.org.</para>
		
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="concepts">
		
		<title>Concepts</title>
		
		<para>The following paragraphs explain some of the Eclipse functionality that Lopb
			relies on to gather benchmarking information.</para>
		
		<sect1 id="jobsJobManagerJobChangeListener">
			
			<title>Jobs, JobManager, JobChangeListener</title>
			
			<para>Since Eclipse version 3.0, plug-in developers are strongly encouraged
				to implement long-running activities as an Eclipse background Jobs <ulink
					url="http://www.eclipse.org/articles/Article-Concurrency/jobs-api.html">
				[1]</ulink> . For example, checking a file out of a source code repository,
				building from an ant script, and publishing an app to an application server
				should be implemented as Eclipse background Jobs by plug-in
				developers.</para>
			
			<para>Jobs get scheduled to run by the JobManager. The JobManager provides a
				callback mechanism so that classes implementing IJobChangeListener will
				be notified when jobs are scheduled, when they complete, or otherwise
				change execution status. The events are instances of
				IJobChangeEvent.</para>
			
			<para>By using this mechanism, Lopb listens for all job change events and when
				they occur, it records the job identifier, a timestamp, and other job data
				which is later used to compute various performance metrics. The overhead
				introduced by Lopb is negligible.</para>
			
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="jobIdsRuns">
			
			<title>JobIds and Runs</title>
			
			<para>When IJobChangeEvents are received by Lopb, a JobId is computed from the
				Job's class and name. We have noticed that plug-in developers often provide
				a short description of the job's behavior instead of a name, and this is
				supported by Lopb. We assume that the class and name pair forms a unique
				identifier for a job, and in practice so far, this assumption has held true.
				Every time a job runs, Lopb keeps track of start and end time along with JobId.
				When a job ends, Lopb determines average execution time for all runs of the
				given JobId, in addition to some other metrics. This data is presented in the
				Lopb Report View.</para>
			
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="concurrectJobsRules">
			
			<title>Concurrent Jobs and Scheduling Rules</title>
			
			<para>Jobs can run concurrently, and may indeed contend for shared resources
				(e.g. workspace files). In order to guard against resource corruption or
				deadlock, scheduling rules are used. At this time, Lopb is not concerned
				with concurrency or scheduling rules since only individual job runs are
				monitored, and not dependencies between jobs or the locks or files that they
				contend for. This may change in the future in order to produce aggregate or
				&quot;roll-up&quot; metrics, see Lopb Status indicator
				(experimental).</para>
			
		</sect1>
		
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="installation">
		
		<title>Installation</title>
		
		<sect1 id="updateManager">
			
			<title>Update Manager</title>
			
			<para>In order to install Lopb using the Eclipse update manager, follow the
				instructions <ulink
					url="http://help.eclipse.org/help33/index.jsp?topic=/org.eclipse.platform.doc.user/tasks/tasks-34.htm">
				here</ulink> and enter http://lopb.org/update as the Eclipse update site
				URL.</para>
			
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="showView">
			
			<title>Show Lopb Views</title>
			
			<para>Upon installation for the first time, the Lopb views will not be visible.
				To enable them, click Window &gt; Show View &gt; Other… then select Lack of
				Progress Bar (Lopb) and one of the two Lopb views. </para>
			<para><inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="@IMAGEDIR@/lopb-show-views.png"
						format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
			
		</sect1>
		
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="lopbFeatures">
		
		<title>Lopb Features</title>
		
		<para>The following few paragraphs describe the features provided by Lopb,
			including the two Eclipse views, and the Eclipse workbench window trim
			contribution (i.e. Lopb Status indicator).</para>
		
		<sect1 id="lopbReportView">
			
			<title>Lopb Report View</title>
			
			<para> The Lopb Report View is the main view provided by Lopb. In the right panel,
				it shows a table of Jobs that have run since the beginning of the development
				session, which is generally when Eclipse started. In the left panel, a set of
				enabled or disabled Labels is shown. When a given label is enabled
				(checked), the jobs associated with that label will appear in the
				table.</para>
			
			<para> <inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="@IMAGEDIR@/lopb-report-view.png"
						format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject></inlinemediaobject> </para>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect2 id="lopbReportViewColumns">
			<title>Lopb Report View: Columns</title>
			<para>
				<table>
					<title>Lopb Report View: Columns</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Column</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>Job</entry>
								<entry>Shows either the jobId (which is derived from the
									class and name of the Job instance) or the jobAlias if
									one exists. This cell is editable so that users may
									modify the displayed text used to identify the job
									(a.k.a. JobAlias). Also see "Enable job renaming"
									in the Lopb Preferences page.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Labels</entry>
								<entry>A comma separated list of labels assigned to a
									Job. Similar to Gmail labels used for organizing
									emails into one or many labels or
									categories.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Runs</entry>
								<entry>The number of times the job has run since the start
									of the session.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Errors</entry>
								<entry>The number of times that the job has returned an
									error code when it completed.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Total time (sec)</entry>
								<entry>The sum of all run times, where each run time is
									equal to the end time minus the start time (in
									seconds).</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Average time (sec)</entry>
								<entry>The total time divided by the number of runs (in
									seconds).</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>System?</entry>
								<entry>Job property indicating whether the job was
									started by an internal Eclipse system routine, or
									not (i.e. user-initiated).</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Blocking?</entry>
								<entry>Job property indicating whether this job is
									blocking a higher priority non-system job from
									starting due to a conflicting scheduling
									rule.</entry>
							</row>
							
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table> </para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="lopbReportViewDropDownMenu">
			<title>Lopb Report View: Drop-down Menu</title>
			<para>In the top right corner of the view, the user may click on a drop-down
				command menu. The available commands are described below.</para>
			<para>
				<table>
					<title>Lopb Report View: Commands</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Command</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>Export to CSV</entry>
								<entry>Export the data from the Lopb Report View table to
									a comma separated value (CSV) file. See the "Output
									directory for exporting CSV files" preference in
									the Lopb Preferences page.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Reset session</entry>
								<entry>Reset the user's session by clearing all jobs
									from the Lopb Report View table and setting all
									timers to zero.</entry>
							</row>
							
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table></para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="lopbReportViewRightClickMenu">
			<title>Lopb Report View: Right-click menu</title>
			<para> By selecting a row and then right-clicking, the user will be able to ignore
				a job from futher processing. This means that Lopb will not collect data for
				any future runs of the Job. </para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect1 id="lopbIgnoredJobsView">
			
			<title>Ignored Jobs View</title>
			
			<para> Users may indicate that they want Lopb to ignore certain jobs (see Lopb
				Report View: Right-click Menu, command Ignore Job). The jobs that have been
				ignored are displayed in the Ignored Jobs View shown below. </para>
			<para><inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="@IMAGEDIR@/lopb-ignoredjobs-view.png"
						format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
			
		</sect1>
		
		<sect2 id="ignoredJobsViewColumns">
			<title>Lopb Ignored Jobs View: Columns</title>
			<para>
				<table>
					<title>Lopb Ignored Jobs View: Columns</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Column</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>Job</entry>
								<entry>The JobId or JobAlias. Same as Lopb Report View,
									Job column, except the cell is not
									editable.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Class</entry>
								<entry>The Job class.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Description</entry>
								<entry>The name or description of the job.</entry>
							</row>
							
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table></para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="lopbIgnoredJobsViewRightClickMenu">
			<title>Lopb Ignored Jobs View: Right-click Menu</title>
			<para> By selecting an ignored job (i.e. row) in the table and then
				right-clicking, the user may remove a job from the list of ignored
				jobs.</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect1 id="lopbStatusIndicator">
			
			<title>Lopb Status Indicator (experimental)</title>
			
			<para>The Lopb Status Indicator is still an experimental feature. It shows an
				aggregate metric of how much of a developer's session is consumed by
				background jobs as a percentage. It is intended to be used as a benchmark
				indicator for system deltas, or rather to compare system performance
				before and after a change like a RAM upgrade or system
				reconfiguration.</para>
			<para> <inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="@IMAGEDIR@/lopb-status-ind.png"
						format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
			
			<para>The Lopb Status Indicator is eventually going to be the "lack of progress
				bar", so the more time developers wait for jobs to complete (by staring at a
				progress bar), the higher the "lack of progress" metric will rise, and vice
				versa. </para>
			<para>This indicator is disabled by default, but it may be enabled by clicking
				the Lopb status checkbox on the Lopb Preference page.</para>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="lopbPreferences">
			
			<title>Lopb Preferences</title>
			
			<para>The user may override certain default behavior for Lopb by changing
				settings in the Lopb Preferences page. To access the page, click Window >
				Preferences and then select Lack of Progress Bar (Lopb). </para>
			<para><inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="@IMAGEDIR@/lopb-preferences.png"
						format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
			
			<para>The preferences that can be modified are described below.
				<table>
					<title>Lopb Preferences</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Preference</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>Include system jobs</entry>
								<entry>When checked, system jobs will be monitored by
									Lopb; otherwise they will be ignored.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Enable job renaming</entry>
								<entry>When checked, Job alias will be editable (first
									column) in the Lopb Report view.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Output directory for exporting CSV
									files</entry>
								<entry>When exporting CSV files, this is the base
									directory for all output files.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Show Lopb status</entry>
								<entry>When checked, the Lopb status indicator will be
									shown in the Eclipse workbench window
									trim.</entry>
							</row>
							
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table> </para>
		</sect1>
		
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="reportingCookbook">
		
		<title>Reporting Cookbook</title>
		
		<para>This section describes various reports that can be produced from the data
			collected by Lopb. At this time, Lopb does not have any built-in reporting
			functionality. The data is exported from Lopb as CSV files, and then processed
			using a spreadsheet tool like MS-Excel in order to produce these
			reports.</para>
		
		<sect1 id="reportExample1">
			
			<title>Report Example 1</title>
			
			<para> Let us assume that Lopb was used to collect data about how long it took to
				check-in files on average for a given developer over the course of a week.
				Then, after an upgrade to the source code repository server, data was
				collected again over the course of a second week. Finally, by plotting the
				average time it took to check in a file for each of the week, the following
				report is produced. </para>
			<para> <inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="@IMAGEDIR@/report-avg-min-cc-checkin.png"
						format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
			
		</sect1>
		
	</chapter>
	
	<appendix id="faq">
		
		<title>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)</title>
		
		<qandaset>
			<qandaentry>
				<question>
					<para>Does it slow down my IDE?</para>
				</question>
				<answer>
					<para>The overhead introduced by Lopb is negligible. We were careful
						to not do any time-consuming processing in the JobManager of
						IJobChangeListener callback handlers. We don’t yet have a factor
						for the overhead, but through a lot of experimentation, we have
						seen that it is very small.</para>
				</answer>
			</qandaentry>
			<qandaentry>
				<question>
					<para>Is it free?</para>
				</question>
				<answer>
					<para>Yes. Lopb is released under the terms of the Eclipse Public
						License, version 1.0 and your are free to download and use the
						software. For further details on what you can or cannot do, please
						read http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html. Note that
						the EPL is a permissive, non-viral open-source license unlike the
						GPL.</para>
				</answer>
			</qandaentry>
		</qandaset>
		
	</appendix>
	
	<appendix id="furtherReading">
		
		<title>Further Reading</title>
		
		<para>We highly recommend Eclipse Plug-ins, 3rd Edition, by Clayberg and Rubel for
			developers interested in building Eclispe plug-ins. We couldn’t have built
			Lopb without it.</para>
		
	</appendix>
	
</book>